Konrad Bercovici Collection
Konrad Bercovici Collection
1925-1964
Bercovici, Konrad, 1882-1961.
2 linear ft.
Romanian-born American author. Manuscripts, memorabilia and correspondence.
2746143
Biographical History
Konrad Bercovici (1882-1961) was a Romanian-American author whose works included biography, travel, history (particularly of Eastern Europe) and fiction. He published his memoirs, It's the Gypsy In Me, in 1941.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Konrad Bercovici Collection consists of writings, memorabilia, and published books.
Writings range from handwritten manuscripts of short stories to galley proofs of novels. Included are several scripts for stage, radio and television production, some of which contain roles performed by Bercovici himself.
Memorabilia contains correspondence, clippings of newspaper and magazine articles, photographs, and flyleaf inscriptions. Correspondence consits of incoming letters from friends and relatives, including Menachem Begin and Louis Nizer..
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged in alphabetical order.
Related Material
The Internet Archive has a freely downloadable copy of It's the Gypsy In Me, available at
http://www.archive.org/details/itsthegypsyinmet010056mbp
.
Separated Material
The collection originally included copies of books written or edited by Bercovici, ranging from Crimes of Passion (1917) to the late 1940s. These have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging; please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Bercovici, Konrad, 1882-1961.; Authors, American.; Authors, Romanian.; Travel writers.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Galley proofs.; Photographs.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Rare Books, 1983.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Against the sky, typescript; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - The American, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - The American, in Country Gentleman, May 1927; printed material (Box 1)
  - Authenticating my portrait by Modigliani, handwritten (Box 1)
  - Authenticating my portrait by Modigliani, 18 May 1905; typed transcript used for publication in The Courier (Box 1)
  - Black wedding, typsecript, annotated (Box 1)
  - Black wedding, television script; typescript annotated (Box 1)
  - Black wedding, miscellaneous pages (Box 1)
  - Conquered, in Delineator Magazine, Dec 1929; printed material (Box 1)
  - Fanica, in Collier's, 16 Jan 1926; printed material (Box 1)
  - Firewood, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - The flood, in Good Housekeeping, Dec 1930; printed material (Box 1)
  - For a song, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Free land, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - The French savage (The savage prodigal), typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Gita, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Gita, in Good Housekeeping, Dec 1930; printed material (Box 1)
  - Horsemen, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Horsemen, in Delineator Magazine, Jan 1928; printed material (Box 1)
  - I'm an American, script no. 27, 24 Nov 1940; copy; transcript of NBC radio broadcast (Box 2)
  - Indian wind, See There is money in poetry
  - Lerla, in Good Housekeeping, Oct 1929; printed material (Box 2)
  - Ludmilla, in Good Housekeeping, Nov 1927; printed material (Box 2)
  - The master, typescript copy (Box 2)
  - The mill on the river, in Good Housekeeping, Jun 1924; printed material (Box 2)
  - Millstones, typescript copy (Box 2)
  - Millstones, in Pictorial Review, Nov 1924; printed material (Box 2)
  - Nancu, in McClure's, undated; printed material (Box 2)
  - Nina, in McCall's, 1929-11; printed material (Box 2)
  - One moment please, in Delineator Magazine, 1927-12; printed material (Box 2)
  - Outcasts, in College Humor, undated; printed material (Box 2)
  - Perta, in Good Housekeeping, undated; printed material (Box 2)
  - Royal intrigue in Romania, in Outlook and Independent, Apr-Jun 1931; printed material (Box 2)
  - Savage prodigal, See The French savage (Box 2)
  - Seed, typescript copy (Box 2)
  - Sirocco, in Country Gentleman, Oct 1926; printed material (Box 2)
  - So beautiful, in The American Magazine, Jan 1930; printed material (Box 2)
  - Steel against steel, in Good Housekeeping, 1925; printed material (Box 2)
  - Story of the Gypsies, typescript, annotated (Box 2)
  - The strong man of the lakes, galley proof (Box 2)
  - The strong man of the lakes, in The American Magazine, May 1930; printed material (Box 2)
  - There is money in poetry, handwritten (Box 2)
  - There is money in poetry, script; typescript, annotated (Box 2)
  - There is money in poetry, television script; mimeograph (Box 2)
  - There is money in poetryin Harper's, undated; printed material (Box 2)
  - There is money in poetry, 22 Feb 1940; "Indian Wind" theatre program, Yale University School of Fine Arts (Box 2)
  - The vineyard, in Good Housekeeping, Jan 1925; printed material (Box 2)
  - What life means to me, photocopy (Box 2)
  - What love is, in Liberty, 13 Feb 1926 (Box 2)
  - What the Gypsies have told me, photocopy (Box 2)
  - When faith returns, typescript copy (Box 2)
  - The whip, in Country Gentleman, Oct 1925; printed material (Box 2)
  - Yeshiva University benefit performance, "Creation", typescript, annotated (Box 2)
  - Youth to Youth, in Delineator Magazine, Nov 1926; printed material (Box 2)
  - Youth to Youth, in The World's One Hundred Best Short Stories, Vol. 4, 1927; printed material (Box 2)
  - Zailain Ladies Home Journal, May 1930 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Correspondence
    Individuals are listed separately but contained in the same folder.
    - Mayfield, John, from Bercovici family and friends (Box 2)
    - Begin, Manachem (Box 2)
    - Bercovici, Jean (Box 2)
    - Bercovici, Rada (Box 2)
    - Bercovici, Rion (Box 2)
    - Birnie, William H. (Box 2)
    - Colin, Rosica (Box 2)
    - Elmo, Ann (Box 2)
    - Farrar, John (Box 2)
    - Finch, Helen (Box 2)
    - Gruenblat, Maxa Nordau (Box 2)
    - Howard, G. Wren (Box 2)
    - Kingdon, Frank (Box 2)
    - Malraux, Andre, by M. Brandin (Box 2)
    - Marshall, Margaret (Box 2)
    - McConnell, Jane T. (Box 2)
    - Nizer, Louis (Box 2)
    - O'Dwyer, Paul (Box 2)
    - Rewald, John (Box 2)
    - Rosenfield, Harry N. (Box 2)
    - Rubin, Reuben (Box 2)
    - Stevens, Roger L. (Box 2)
    - Wheeler, Monroe, by Francis Keech (Box 2)
    - Facsimiles of Misc. Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Flyleaf inscriptions (Box 3)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles about Bercovici
    - Guyon, Louise Hubert. "Konrad Bercovici." Boston Globe, 15 Aug 1925 (Box 3)
    - Hewes, Robert E. "Bercovici gives writer's views." Los Angeles Times, undated (Box 3)
    - Janacek, Pat. "Rada Bercovici contributes father's collection to University." Daily Orange, 31 Oct 1963 (Box 3)
    - Mayfield, John. "Konrad Bercovici." The Courier, Mar 1964 (Box 3)
    - Miller, Arthur. "Master of irony." Los Angeles Times Sunday Magazine, 05 Feb 1939 (Box 3)
    - Noel, David. "Konrad Bercovici." The Scholastic, 10 Jan 1925 (Box 3)
    - Obituary. New York Times, 28 Dec 1961 (Box 3)
    - "Romany tales." Saturday Evening Post, undated (Box 3)
    - "The short story changes." The New York Nation, 30 Nov 1961 (Box 3)
    - Swan, Gilbert. "In New York." Syracuse Herald, 25 May 1931 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, of Bercovici, taken by Margrethe Mather and Muray; also of two portraits of Bercovici, painted by Mirel Bercovici Abbott and Modigliani. (Box 3)
  - Three Lively Arts, contains article by Mirana Bercovici Abbott (Box 3)